Great. So, we had some uh feedback in
office hours and other times that it
might be helpful to have like a highle
recap of the algorithms that we've
talked about so far to try to understand
where some of the pieces fit together.
Uh so, I put together one slide that um
is a little bit more high level but
actually captures almost all the
algorithms that we've seen so far. Uh
and in particular we've talked about
both online and offline algorithms where
online refers to scenarios where the
policy will be used to collect data and
offline means that we're given a data
set and we cannot do any additional data
collection in our environment.
And uh in the offline setting we talked
about um two different classes of
reinforcement learning methods uh that
use on policy data collection in order
to improve. We referred to the first
type as on policy RL and the second type
as off policy RL uh where on policy RL
you can collect data but only from uh
the current policy. You can only use
data from the current policy. And this
is means that you are not going to be
reusing past data. You're not going you
can't use offline data and so forth. Um,
and this included algorithms like
reinforce or the vanilla policy gradient
method.
And then within the realm of off policy
RL, this was where we could start to
reuse data from other policies,
including data from policies uh before
we took a gradient step on our policy
parameters. Uh, and this included
algorithms like PO and important
sampling. Uh and then we talked about
algorithms that are more off policy that
can uh reuse data from policies that are
even different even more different uh
and where we use a replay buffer to
store the data from those past policies
and that included algorithms like DQN
and SACE.
Um and then I colored these different
algorithms different colors uh because
the blue algorithms um only involve
training a policy and so we refer to
them as policy gradient methods. uh PO
and SACE learn both a policy and a
critic uh and so we refer to them as
actor critic methods uh and there's also
algorithms that only learn a critic and
don't explicitly learn a separate policy
uh and that those are often referred to
as Q-learning algorithms such as DQM. I
should also mention that PO is often
actually referred to as a policy
gradient method. Uh although you do
actually learn a value function and so
we typically we're referring to it as
actor critic uh in this class to avoid
confusion.
Um and then separate from these classes
of online methods we also have offline
RL methods that we started talking
about. Um and these built upon a lot of
the ideas we saw in online RL um but I
have to cope with the fact that you're
not collecting any data at all. uh and
we looked at two different approaches
there. One is to constrain to only
considering actions in the data. Um and
this included algorithms like AWR um
AWAC and IQL uh and also an algorithm
like CQL that implicitly is constraining
you to actions in the data um but not um
but not so explicitly and and this is
through conservatism.
Now um for these RL algorithms um
generally as you move right uh you need
more online data uh and so that means
that typically you need you're they're
going to be kind of more expensive
because online data is often more
expensive than offline data uh because
you can't um it's harder to kind of
repeatedly collect a large amount of
online data.
Um and then lastly before we talked
about Earl we also talked about
imitation learning algorithms and uh
this can also fall within the bucket of
offline and online although there
there's a bit different set of
assumptions. Um the first imitation
learning algorithm we covered was kind
of vanilla behavior cloning uh where
we're taking a data set and trying to
imitate the act the actions in that data
set. Um and then we also talked about an
online algorithm that uh is online both
in terms of the policy and in terms of
querying an expert like asking an expert
what is the right action on this new
data that I'm collecting. Um and I put
these in kind of a they're in a little
bit of a separate category because um
they have different assumptions. You
don't need a reward function. Um, but
you do need pretty good data. Uh, and
you you're not going to be able to
outperform uh the average behavior in
your data set.
Um, cool. So, that's kind of an overview
um including a lot of these different
terms that we see in reinforcement
learning like offline, online, um, off
policy, on policy, uh, and so forth and
imitation learning versus reinforcement
learning.
Cool. Um, so what we're going to talk
about today is we're going to talk about
modelbased reinforcement learning. Uh,
and model based reinforcement learning
can actually be applied to all of the
different classes of reinforcement
learning methods on the previous slide.
Uh, someone has a special place in my
heart because I um I used to do actually
quite a bit of work on modelbased RL and
I think that there's a lot of really
cool things that you can do with model
based reinforcement learning. Uh, we'll
talk about the key idea behind it. um
how to learn models, how to use those
models um including with planning and
data generation. And then we'll also
look at one case study index robot
manipulation. Um and as a teaser for
that, uh we'll talk about um the methods
that we'll be talking about today is
we'll allow a robot to do something like
this. Uh which is pretty cool. This hand
has more than 20 degrees of freedom,
more than 20 different joints that it's
controlling. Um yeah and then kind of
the key outcomes is trying to understand
how we can learn and use dynamics models
and the different challenges and
trade-offs with this whole class of
methods.
Cool. Um so the key idea behind
modelbased reinforcement learning is uh
essentially we're going to try to learn
a simulator. Uh can we learn how to
predict the future
for actions that we might be taking?
Uh and for robotics and and driving and
other physical systems uh this might be
um modeling the physics of some
particular system uh if you can directly
observe the underlying um kind of
physical entities in that system. Uh and
um alternatively, if you can't directly
observe the different entities in that
physical system um and model them, then
this might look something more like
video prediction conditioned on actions
that the agent wants to take. Um so for
example, um I might want to predict if I
say something to um someone else, how
will they react? Or if I for example
move my legs in a certain way, will I
fall down? Will I go that way? Will I go
that way? Uh and so forth.
Um, in terms of like what this video
prediction might actually look like, uh,
the we've seen like pretty cool videos
coming out of, uh, large models like V2
and Sora. Uh, and these are kind of
examples of,
uh, generated images, videos, videos
that are generated by a neural network.
Uh and you can imagine that these kinds
of models could be very useful for
training um systems like cars, robots,
um quadrotors that are flying through um
different places uh in order to learn
about how their actions affect the
world.
Um now models could look something like
models of the physical world. They could
also look at models of other things. So
uh for example, if you wanted to learn a
policy to make money on the stock
market, then um one of these simulators
would be trying to predict what will
happen to the stock market over time and
if your actions have any effect on that.
Um and then if you're trying to train an
agent to play a game, uh then this sort
of model will underscore the rules of
that game. And actually in a lot of
games you might actually already know
the rules of the game and you may not
even need to learn a model in the first
place. Uh for example in chess if you
take a particular action um you know the
outcome you know how the piece will move
as a result of that action. Um and then
it comes down to uh in two-player games
or three-player games or multiplayer
games um you might need to model other
players. Uh modeling other players you
can sometimes consider that as part of
the dynamics but often times it's
actually modeled separately. Um so you
don't even even necessarily um need to
consider it as part of this simulator of
the world and you for example you might
be able to use your own the model of
yourself as a model of another agent.
Okay so if we can learn a simulator um
how would we use it? So the sketch of an
algorithm would be something like this
where we get some data. Uh then we learn
a simulator on that data that's going to
be trying to predict the future uh for
the present and some action that I might
take from the present and then try to
run your favorite method inside the
simulator.
Um so for example um maybe you have a
kind of a simple scenario where you want
to get from the green point to the red
point. Um you might collect some data.
Um this is collected from some policy.
Then you would train some neural network
conditioned on a state and an action.
What is the next state?
Um, and one way that you could learn
this is just by uh minimizing the L2
loss between your predicted next state
and the next state observed in the data.
And then um in terms of running your
favorite RL method, you could use one of
the RL methods that we've covered. Um or
you could use a planning method. And
we'll talk about a couple planning
methods today.
Um cool. So now I have a question for
you. So here's a sketch of an algorithm.
Uh does anyone have thoughts on what
might go wrong if you follow this
sketch? Yeah. So um the [clears throat]
idea there was that your simulator might
not always be accurate and so similar to
what we saw in reward modeling and also
arguably what we saw when training Q
functions. Uh you might exploit those
inaccuracies. those inaccuracies might
compound and then what you've learned in
your kind of learn simulator might not
transfer to the real scenario that
you're trying to learn a good policy in.
Yeah. So there's also this data coverage
issue. So um similar to what we've seen
when training Q functions and other
things uh if this pi zero if this
initial policy doesn't um is different
from the policy that you're ultimately
learning then you're going to have this
mismatch and you might not have coverage
of um you might model might not be
accurate for uh the states that are
visited by the policy that you're
learning. Cool. So um
the this is mostly what basically what's
on the slide exactly. So if you have um
some environment, maybe you want to
navigate a maze, uh then you might uh
collect some data set from some policy.
Maybe the policy does something like
this yellow arrow. This is your data
set. Uh but this data set doesn't cover
the whole maze. And so then if you
wanted to go to this part of the maze,
for example, or this part of the maze,
then you your model probably wouldn't be
very accurate about the mazes in those
parts of the environment. And so then
you wouldn't be able to learn a policy
for reaching those parts of the maze.
Um and then for the second point, um you
might not always have an accurate
simulator. So here's an example of a
video generated by Sora um with the
prompt, a humanoid robot standing near a
table with a red, green, and blue cubes
on it performs a cube stacking task with
red on the bottom and blue on the top.
Uh and you can see that the uh video
generation does some creative things
with physics where uh it kind of changes
the colors of the block uh and
synthesizes blocks out of thin air. Uh I
would love for my robot to be able to do
something like this. Uh seems very
useful. Uh but this is not kind of
modeling uh what robots can actually do
in reality.
Uh and to this point, when you're
actually trying to develop this kind of
model, uh oftentimes you might need to
make choices that are dependent on the
domain. Like if you're trying to train a
video prediction model versus training a
model of um of of like kind of low-level
physics with friction or training a
model of the stock market, uh you might
have some choices to make in terms of
what are the inputs to that model and
how are you training it, what's the
architecture and so forth. Um, and some
domains are going to be much easier to
simulate than others.
Uh, and then lastly for this last part,
uh, even if you have a really good
simulator, uh, this doesn't mean that
it'll be easy to get a good policy, um,
or to get actions that are accurate. As
a result, you still have to run, you
still have to do the RL process, uh,
using the simulator. Uh, and you need to
account for inaccuracies in the model
during this process. uh because usually
your model is not perfect. You don't
have a a perfect simulator of the world.
That's the key idea behind modelbased
RL. Um now let's talk a little briefly
about how to learn a dynamics model. Um
we don't have too much time to cover
this so we'll just talk about it briefly
and then we'll spend most of the time on
how to use a dynamics model. Okay. Um so
in terms of learning a good simulator or
a good dynamics model uh there are some
scenarios where you might know it
already uh and you could already you
could just use it um [snorts] and then
you're in great shape. Uh there's also
scenarios where you might actually know
most of the model. Um like if you are in
a a simplified
um robotic control setting uh where
you're trying to like push an object on
a table, maybe you know most of it, but
you don't know the friction of the
table, the friction coefficient of the
table. or um in driving maybe you have a
pretty good model of how the car is
going to like accelerate like how it
will move forward if um with like a
given like steer steering command and a
gearing a given thing and you just um
need to model some additional things. Uh
in those cases you might actually be
able to leverage knowledge that you know
about the world and then fit those
unknown parameters using the data. Uh
this is actually I think one of the
cooler ways to try to incorporate domain
specific knowledge uh into reinforcement
learning algorithms.
Uh and then in almost all scenarios in
practice you don't really know the
model. Um, and this might be because you
c you can't, for example, if you're
trying to like um manipulate some
objects, maybe you kind of know roughly
the laws of physics, but you don't know
like the vast majority of like how an
object is going to behave because it has
lots of different properties and there's
many different objects. Um, or you don't
know how people are going to interact in
the world or other drivers are going to
behave in the world and so forth. Um and
in these scenarios uh the typical
practice is to learn the model from
scratch with a neural network um or um
some other function approximator.
Um
now there are a couple options here as
well. So the if you are using like image
observations for example and you're
trying to predict like uh like if your
your state space for example is like an
image of um I don't know maybe this is
like uh you have a car and there's like
other cars here uh and you're trying to
predict uh like in video like where
those cars will be moving uh in the
future. And maybe there's like I don't
know some like trash on the ground or
something like that. Uh one option is to
uh this I'll refer to this image as ST.
Uh one option is to generate like
entire future video
like like the videos that we saw on the
previous slide. This would be
conditioned on
actions.
Uh but this might be fairly expensive to
do. Uh because you have to if you have
to basically be predicting this entire
video over time. Uh that's a pretty
large thing and you have to model all
the different details of how all of the
pixels are going to change in the
future.
And so one alternative option uh that is
sometimes used in uh to learn dynamics
models is instead of modeling in the
image space you could instead learn some
lower dimensional representation and
then model in that representation space.
So you for example uh could learn for a
given state you could learn some sort of
encoder that maps this to a lower
dimensional representation space maybe
we'll refer to this as ZT
and then instead of learning a model in
the original image space we could then
try to learn a model that predicts
uh future ZTS like ZT plus one
Um
this can be a good alternative in
scenarios where it seems like it'll be
very expensive to learn um a full model.
It also has its own challenges because
you need to figure out how to get this
representation in the first place. Um
and if you have a good way to get good
representations um it can be a good
choice. Yeah. So the question was um we
are going to be losing information by
going to a lower dimension and so is the
main reason to do this in terms of cost?
Um yeah and exactly. So the main reason
to do this is to try to reduce like some
of the computational cost associated
with this because um you are losing um
you might be losing information. Uh and
the key idea is that there is some parts
of this observation that doesn't matter.
Um like uh perhaps like the exact
texture of the road um like whether it's
like really dark black or or or maybe a
little bit worn down. In many scenarios
that might not matter. And so if you can
learn a representation that discards
that information that's irrelevant um
then you don't have to spend so much
compute modeling all those details that
don't matter.
The other thing that I'll mention here
is that often times when you're trying
to learn these models uh typically with
supervised learning or generative
modeling techniques uh you often will
also need to learn a reward model as
well. Uh and the reason for this is that
if you want to be using your model to
generate data um or to kind of see into
the future uh you need to see into the
future not just the states but also how
those predicted states will lead to
rewards. Um and so we'll talk about um
what that looks like uh on the next
couple slides. Uh the question is does
model learning have to happen end to
end? Uh the way that it works is we are
optimizing for our ability to generate
future states. Uh and
the there are actually pros and cons
that we'll talk about with regard to
that objective. Uh but you can think of
it as like how well one way to think
about it is like how well can I model
the distribution of ps1
given st.
Uh, another way to think about it,
especially if you have more
deterministic dynamics, is um how well
can I minimize the uh the error between
my predicted ST+1
and the
uh like the actual ST+1.
So, how do we go about using a dynamics
model? Um the
the first approach that we'll talk about
is we'll actually start by talking about
planning. And so this is actually going
to be a little bit different than simply
running reinforcement learning inside
your kind of learn simulator.
And
the way that this could work is
you can think about your MDP where you
have uh your current state that you're
in and then you take some action and
then this affects your
next action and then as a result of that
you'll also get some future reward. uh
and then this process will repeat.
You'll get uh you'll take another action
that influences the state after that
which will yield uh some additional
reward. This reward might also depend on
uh the action that you took as well.
Now the
often can in some of the past
reinforcement learning works that we
talked about we kind of assumed that we
didn't really know this kind of the
relationship. we kind of don't know how
the actions affect future states and so
we have to figure out how to optimize
rewards without using kind of direct
gradients.
But if we can actually predict
uh like what a future state is uh and
what a reward is based off of that. If
we train a reward model and a dynamics
model, then we could actually just
directly back propagate from rewards
into
actions. Um, and so we could potentially
kind of directly pass gradients um from
uh your rewards into your actions. And
what this would look like is your
objective would be to maximize
the
um either just the current action or
maybe uh the kind of next sequence of
actions
for the sum of future rewards. Uh maybe
we'll do this t prime from uh for some
horizon. So maybe uh we're optimizing
for the rewards from time t to time t
plus h.
So what this would look like
specifically
um I guess we can show it on the slides
as well. So we're trying to maximize the
sum of rewards and
uh we often refer to this kind of
problem as a kind of looking into the
future is planning a sequence of actions
that will maximize rewards. And so if we
have some model of how uh how we predict
future states and actions and rewards
and we if we're modeling that with a
with a neural network then we can also
compute the gradients of that neural
network to back propagate rewards into
actions um as following.
And so then specifically what this would
look like is
uh well first you would
collect some data
then you would train your model.
Um maybe that's to minimize
f of sa minus the this is your predicted
next state. This is your true next
state.
And then once you have this model you
could then
uh find a set of actions that is
actually just to be explicit for this
optimization we're minimizing the
parameters of our model.
And then the third step is to try to
find a set of actions.
So this would be um a hat
t to t plus h. This is like what is the
course of actions that will lead to good
rewards. Um and this would be
the argmax
um of the um
of the sum of rewards.
Well, sum of t and this is over uh
so you might this is um writing gradient
descent on actions is a little bit like
back propagation to actions is a little
bit different from the typical backrop
that we look at. So often times when we
run back prop we're doing it with regard
to parameters of a neural network. Here
we're actually back propagating into
these actions right here. And so
specifically what this kind of third
step would look like is you would
um you would need to basically like
initialize
just like you like randomly initialize
your neural network parameters, you'll
need to initialize your actions.
Then you need to compute your gradient.
So this would be
the gradient
of the sum of rewards
with respect to
the actions that you take. And to
compute this gradient, this would be you
can think of it essentially like if you
use the chain rule, the gradient will be
uh the sum of rewards with respect to
the states.
Um so that would just be based off of
your reward model. And then you'll have
uh then if you apply the chain rule you
could then um have a second term that's
d states d actions to actually get the
gradient of the rewards with respect to
the actions.
And then once you have your gradient
then
you could use it to update your actions
with gradient descent. And so then
uh maybe this is your initial a hat. Um
a hat t to t plus h is going to be your
previous
a hat
minus alpha times this gradient right
here.
I'm going to put this separately.
Yeah, great question. Actions would be
continuous in this setting. Yeah. Um
we'll also look at scenarios where we
can do it with with discrete actions as
well. We're assuming rewards are
deterministic, but we've actually always
assumed rewards are deterministic. Um
and you can have you can consider any
sort of non-determinism being
encapsulated by the dynamics and in the
state variable. Correct. Yeah. So here
we have a dynamics model and I yeah I
guess I didn't explicitly write this but
um right you also need to have you would
also be trading some reward function. Um
maybe this is like uh RSI for example.
Um and this we this would be using like
some of the reward learning techniques
that we've talked about. There's also
some scenarios where you might know the
reward. Um so it might be for example um
like forward velocity if you're trying
to learn how to walk um or some distance
to some goal that sort of thing. And in
those cases you don't need to learn a
reward function. Yeah. So the question
is um if your dynamics model is
stochastic how do you back prop it? uh
that gets into
a lot of the like it kind of depends on
how you're modeling the stoasticity. So
um if you're using a gausian for example
there are certain tricks for
differentiating through samples from
that gausian um whereas if you're using
something like a diffusion model uh it
would look a bit different. Uh so the it
it is kind of model dependent uh and so
far uh we are we're talking about
deterministic models. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So I so the question is will this
like start to exploit errors in the
reward? Yeah. So this will start to
exploit both errors in the reward but
also errors in the dynamics model. So uh
the if your dynamics model is inaccurate
uh or if your reward model is
inaccurate, if either one of them is
inaccurate, then you might get actions
that aren't actually going to take good
actions in the world. Uh and that's a
problem. Uh and so we'll talk about that
in a second. Yeah. So this is a good
question. So, um I guess instead of
repeating it, I think what would be
helpful is um we aren't actually
learning a policy here. And that's
essentially what you're pointing out. Uh
and
and this is essentially
um this is now this is like becoming our
policies uh quote unquote. Um this is
like our behavior and the um did I have
a good term for this? I guess I mean
yeah this is like sort of
the policy uh in quotes uh and this is
what we call planning where at every
single state we're actually going to be
planning forward and thinking ahead like
what are the actions I should consider
that I think will lead to good reward uh
and and so we'll actually be doing this
optimization process every single state
uh when we're doing planning
um so on this slide. Uh we're going to
be running some policy to collect data,
learning a model to uh try to be able to
accurately model the dynamics,
potentially also learning a reward
function as well.
Uh and then we'll be back propagating
through um the reward and the dynamics
in order to choose actions.
Uh and then once we choose those actions
um we'll be then be executing these
actions in the environment. Uh and then
after we execute those actions we'll
then be rerunning this planning process
again. Uh so in particular I guess maybe
to explicitly write that out uh we'll
have a step four here that is to
actually
execute
uh a hat t to t plus h. uh and then you
will uh kind of then kind of move on
back to step three after you've executed
these h actions.
Yeah. So the question is um we are only
planning over a horizon of h and what if
we have an infinite horizon? Uh the
in principle you can like the math kind
of well
it's a good question. Um what what how
so we'll talk a little bit about this.
Um for now we're going to be only
considering this short horizon planning.
Um
and like in like eightish slides or
something I'll talk a little bit more
about like what happens if you want to
do infinite or very long horizon things.
Um and we'll also talk about some of the
the shortcomings of this. Yeah.
Okay.
Now, so far we've been talking about
like we talked about kind of gradient
descent for optimizing actions. Uh and
this is actually not the only way that
you can do optimization. So it's
probably the optimization technique that
you're most familiar with uh because we
use it all the time for neural networks.
But uh there's other ways that we can
optimize a function. Uh specifically
when we're trying to optimize the sum of
rewards.
Uh and uh if we think about gradient
based optimization uh typically we have
um something we're trying to optimize
over in this case it would be uh we're
trying to be optimizing over actions and
the thing that we're trying to optimize
is um the sum of rewards
maybe. Yeah. Um and so
actually also there's a small mistake
here. There should be a plus sign
because we're maximizing not minimizing.
Um
so the way that gradient descent works
is you kind of randomly initialize some
action like right here and then you
evaluate the gradient at that position.
So maybe you find that the gradient is
like pointed like this way. Uh and then
you then say okay I should move probably
over here. And then maybe you sample
this. you choose this action because
that's kind of a step size away. You
evaluate the gradient there and you find
that the gradient maybe looks something
like this. Uh and then okay, you say
okay maybe I should move further to left
but a little bit less because this the
slope is less steep. And then you get um
maybe something that looks like this.
And you're like okay I'm um the gradient
is zero and so maybe I won't be sampling
any further actions. And then your final
choice uh after writing gradient descent
is this value right here.
Now an alternative way to samp to try to
do a kind of optimization is instead
what I'll call sampling based
optimization. This is also called
gradientfree optimization.
And the way that this works is if you
have some set of actions and some sum of
rewards
you instead of just starting from one
place and evaluating the gradient. We're
actually not going to use the gradients
at all and we'll just sample a bunch of
actions and see what the values are. So
maybe we'll for example sample like this
action. We'll sample uh this action. Uh
maybe sample this one. Um maybe sample
this one. Uh and so forth.
And
the first version of kind of a sampling
based method could just be to sample a
bunch of actions a bunch of things in
parallel and then pick the best one. Uh
this is sometime is basically just
called random sampling. Uh sometimes it
actually works like better than you
think it might do. And if we were to do
that then we would say that okay this
action has the highest and so maybe I
will kind of return the corresponding
action for this value.
Uh but you can also do something a bit
better than that even without gradient
optimization which is that you could
look at these samples and say okay it
looks like uh maybe like maybe we have
one more one additional sample thing
that we've maybe we've also like sampled
something like this. Um and in that
case, one thing that we could do is
instead of just uh considering this one
and taking the best is we could say
maybe we should sample more over here uh
because these are the ones that that
were the best. And so we could fit uh
we could basically try to sample more
from the things that were good. So we
could take the ones that were the best
fit some kind of distribution over those
like a simple distribution like a
gausian say that okay these were the
actions that were the best. So maybe we
could fit um some gausian or sample more
from the actions here and then do
another round of sampling from that new
distribution where now you're going to
be sampling more from this distribution.
You find that like when you sample for a
second round maybe you get um samples
that look like this. Uh and then that
allows you to hone in on what a good
action might be.
So on the slides um I did this on the
slides instead of with actions and
maximizing rewards. I did it with
parameters and minimizing some loss
function. Uh but all the ideas are the
same. So for gradient descent we pick an
initial value evaluate the gradient move
in the direction of the gradient and
repeat that process. There's some
underlying function that we don't know.
uh and I and so we're trying to get to
the minimum of that function using these
gradients.
And likewise with sampling or another
way to call this is a zeroth order
optimization. We're instead going to be
sampling points and uh trying to figure
out what a good value is just from
sampling. Uh and again there is some
underlying curve here uh that we don't
know. we can we can only evaluate
samples or or in the case of gradient
descent uh the gradient of those
samples.
One other nice thing about a sampling
based optimization is that it means that
you don't need gradients. Uh so it can
apply to discrete variables. It can also
apply to scenarios where you maybe know
the reward function some like you know
you have reward values but you don't
know what the gradient of the reward
function is.
um like if it's a discrete like one if
it's a discrete uh reward function then
getting the gradient might be
challenging.
Okay. And then to formalize this kind of
iterative sampling process where we're
trying to sample more from the good
actions. Uh one method for doing this is
cross entropy method. Uh there's also a
way to do this with well if you have
discrete actions uh you could also just
um well there's somewhat of a different
process but you could also just use
random sampling if your action space is
small enough. Um so what uh cross
entropy method does not to be confused
with the cross entropy loss is you
sample from some initial distribution.
This could be a uniform distribution.
Then rank the samples according to their
loss
um to get the um like this would be the
best one. This would be the second best,
this third best, fourth best and so
forth. And then take the best ones like
these three ones and then fit a
distribution like a Gaussian
distribution to those best samples
and then reample from your distribution.
rerank and repeat this process.
So it's basically like a very simple uh
sampling based way to try to get um in
this case good actions. It can it's a
kind of a general optimization technique
that could be used for um any sort of
objective.
Now um cool and then after this process
eventually um after you run some number
of iterations you'll return uh the best
sample that you found in the last
iteration.
Uh the question is can you also use
sampling to approximate gradients? Um
yes. So there is a way there's something
called finite differences. Uh where if
you don't have a way to get gradients
then you could try to sample basically
points very close together and then use
that to basically like look at the
difference between like this point and
this point and uh use that to estimate
the gradient. Um there's pros and cons
to to it but there's definitely a valid
approach. Yeah. Uh the reason the
question is why do I put the quotes
around the policy here? Um the reason is
that we're not like learning a
parametric policy. We're not like
learning a neural network to represent a
policy. Um and there's actually like an
a pro like an optimization process
underlying the policy uh here. And so
typically we don't um it's a policy in
the sense that it is mapping from a
state to an action or a state to
actually multiple future actions. Um but
it's often not referred to a policy um
because to differentiate it from
policies that are like more like neural
network like that are like more compact.
Um well you can also have like a a
linear function that's mapping states to
actions. It's the main thing is that
it's a process. It's like an iterative
optimization process rather than some
sort of like closed form like here's an
action for a state. Yeah. So the
question is can we talk a little bit
about how this policy is stored? So um
the the only thing that we have learned
at this point is a dynamics model and
potentially a reward function. Uh and so
the only thing that we have stored is
the parameters of the model and the
parameters of your reward model. uh the
and then when you're actually trying to
to figure out what to do uh and and what
actions to take, what what policy to
follow uh we don't have a neural network
that's telling us what actions to take.
Instead, every single time step, you're
thinking, okay, what's going to happen
if I do this, this, or this? Uh and then
choosing actions that you think are good
as a result of that kind of thinking
process. uh this ends up being like
you're using a lot more compute as part
of this process and you're doing that
like in real time uh as you're trying to
figure out what actions to take. Yeah.
So we're not recording um we're not
recording what we're doing. Yeah. Right
now. Yeah. Yeah. So the question is um
if we when we sample actions if some of
them are like can some of them be out of
distribution? So yeah, when you select
the distribution to sample from, um,
your actions might be out of
distribution compared to the data that
the model was trained on. And we'll talk
a bit, we'll talk in like the next slide
on how to deal with that. Yeah. Yeah. So
the question is um because we're doing
so much compute at test time uh if if
you finished computing and by the time
you finish computing the state has
changed, how do you account for that? uh
the
typically I don't know if I have a great
answer for you. I think that typically
um when people run this in practice they
just try to um make that compute process
as fast as possible uh so that um they
don't have to account for the change. I
guess one thing that I one thing you can
do uh is
you're kind of planning actually a
sequence of actions here. And so if you
know that um if you can estimate how
long your um how long that computation
took if it took like two time steps for
example then instead of starting by
executing a you could actually start by
executing a plus three um or a plus two
uh depending on how yeah the off by one
works. Uh and so that's kind of
accounting for the fact that like you
have like time has moved forward. The
downside there is that um at and at
plus1 might be different from what was
actually executed and so you might be in
a different state from where you thought
you ended up in. Uh, and so that
introduces challenges. And it's actually
somewhat of an open research problem on
like how best to handle that sort of um
like uh that sort of thing especially if
you're um you're like basically kind of
asynchronously like running this process
and also like the world is uh evolving
as well.
Okay. So um in terms of so going back to
gradient like doing this with gradient
descent versus with samples the um
there's pros and cons to gradient based
and sampling based and this helps
elucidate why sampling based actually
can be a good choice for planning. So
gradient descent is uh very scalable
even to very high dimensions. Uh and it
works well especially in overp
parameterized regimes like when you have
a big neural network that's representing
a function that may actually have fewer
free parameters.
The downside is it requires a nice
optimization landscape where um your
kind of gradients are fairly smooth
rather than um rather than not smooth I
guess. uh with neural networks it ends
up being um especially because neural
networks have high dimensional parameter
spaces and are over parameterized um
kind of the pros end up heavily
outweighing the cons here. Some of the
upsides with sampling based approaches
is that it's really easy to parallelize
because you can actually like um
estimate multiple samples in parallel.
Whereas gradient descent it's inevitably
has to be a very sequential process
where you compute one gradient and then
apply it and then compute the next
gradient and so forth. And this
parallelization can actually in some
cases make it faster. Uh it doesn't
require gradients if you don't have
them. Um the downside is that it scales
poorly to high dimensions because if you
have a really high dimensional space,
it's very hard to cover that
highdimensional space with lots of
different samples. So in one dimensions
um something like this can actually work
really really well. Uh but if you can
imagine um instead of this being
onedimensional or two-dimensional or 10
dimensional you have to um you have to
have your samples cover that space well
in order to find um a good optimum.
Cool. So what the what specifically what
um the planning approach would look like
with a sampling based optimization is
you will still run some policy and train
some model like we did in the first two
steps and we'll also be choosing actions
that are trying to maximize rewards. So
um essentially things are the same
except the way that we do this
optimization problem is going to change
where instead of uh instead of running
gradient descent we could instead sample
a bunch of different actions imagine
what will happen in the future and what
rewards we'll get and then um
potentially refine uh our selection of
actions uh iteratively to then get a
good outcome.
Um and so uh in terms of what this looks
like uh if we use capital a as shorthand
to denote this kind of uh a t to a t
plus h then
um version one is if we just do one
round of sampling then we'll sample a
large number of possible action choices
we could take from some distribution
then choose choose the set of actions
that had the highest reward.
Um, and then run those actions in the
environment. Um, this is the technical
name for this is often called random
shooting because you're kind of shooting
out different possible samples of what
could happen in the future, imagining
the future, evaluating the reward, and
then just picking the one uh the one
shot that had the highest reward.
Now
the kind of the the downside and the
thing that's kind of um unsatisfying
about this first algorithm is that this
distribution may not be very good. Uh
and so what we could do is we could use
the cross entropy method where we're
iteratively improving that distribution
where we start from some distribution,
maybe a uniform distribution, evaluate
um rank and pick the best samples that
have the highest rewards.
um and then refit a new distribution to
those best samples and repeat that
process where we're then going to be
resampling from that more uh that better
distribution uh and then evaluating
those samples uh and repeating.
Um if this is paralyzed, this process
actually can be quite fast. Um if you
have um lowdimensional actions, it's
actually also pretty simple uh to
implement. Um, but like we talked about,
it doesn't scale well to high
dimensions. Uh, and so it's best if you
have a somewhat um kind of
lowdimensional space that you're
considering. This includes both h and a
because the optimization that you're
considering is over um this vector right
here. And you need to be um the size of
this is the dimensionality of your
action space times the horizon.
Cool.
Let's run through an example um for
roughly how this would work. So
let's say that we are in this simple
beautiful environment uh and you are
trying to maximize reward. Maybe you're
trying to get to the highest point uh
because the highest point you get the
nicest view. Uh so the reward is just
like the height of of where you get to.
Um you run some policy, you collect some
data like this. Uh and maybe you learn
that um when you kind of train a model
on this data that when you move right
then you go higher. Uh because generally
when you move right kind of the
elevation became higher.
And then when you then kind of try to
choose actions according to your model,
then you're going to learn that you
should go right. Uh so you'll learn um
that when you're actually kind of
finding actions that maximize reward,
you'll your set of actions will be to go
right.
And then um then you'll actually execute
those actions uh and you'll go right. Uh
which is good for a bit. uh you'll be
maximizing reward for a while and then
at some point uh you'll fall off the
cliff and that's not so good.
Um and this is because the thing that we
talked about at the very beginning
there's this data distribution mismatch
where the data that you collected at the
beginning doesn't cover the data that
you are taking with your final policy.
Uh so we have a simple fix to this. Uh
the simple fix is that when we then
execute actions in our environment, we
can then
add those actions to our data set and
refit our model to that data set, learn
a more accurate model, and repeat this
process. Um, and so then this is
starting to look a little bit more uh
like a reinforcement learning algorithm
because we're actually iteratively
collecting data, fitting a better model,
in this case a dynamics model, uh,
sampling actions, choosing actions to
execute, and and running those actions
in the environment.
Um, and so then when we do this, we will
then execute the actions that we
planned. So we'll go off the cliff. Then
we'll learn that our model will become
more accurate. We'll learn that if we go
right past this point, we get um a lot
of negative rewards or we get a lot of
um like very low elevation which
corresponds to negative rewards. Um and
then we'll be able to learn a model that
um goes to the top and stops.
Cool. Um
now
there's a number of things that we could
still improve about this algorithm.
Um, and let's talk about a few of those.
So,
so far we've been executing
this kind of set of actions right here
in the environment. So, we've been
planning out a sequence of actions um,
executing them. And so, what that looks
like is we have
we have our agent
and our agent is like
We're running h actions in the
environment. Uh so action at a at plus1
a t+2 and so forth uh in some
environment
and we're executing those actions
without actually having access to the
previous the kind of intermediate
states.
And one um one alternative that you can
consider is something where uh at each
time we're going to be planning uh a t
to a t plus h. But we could also have
something where we plan uh
a t to t plus h but we only actually
execute a t in the environment.
And then we then get another uh the next
state back in return. And then we replan
at the next time step a new set of
actions.
And so uh the difference between these
two things, this is often what's called
open loop. uh because you're not
actually using the feedback from the
environment the the intermediate STS
when you are
uh executing future actions whereas this
is often called closed loop uh because
you're able to use you're actually kind
of replanning as you get new states.
So here's what that looks like. Now I'm
curious um does anyone have thoughts on
like scenarios in which it might be bad
to be open loop like this where you're
not using uh kind of you're not you're
only planning based off of ST and not
planning based off of all of the kind of
future STS. Yeah. So when the
environment is changing a lot. So if the
environment changed in a way that is
different from what you anticipated
because you maybe weren't able to
predict everything that would happen,
then you won't react to [snorts] those
changes when you act in an openloop way.
Uh and instead if you're closed loop and
you're reconsidering based off of the
latest states, then you're able to uh
actually react to those changes and um
potentially in some cases actually uh uh
have a much much better policy. Whereas
in scenarios where um the world is like
a little bit more deterministic, it can
be okay to be a little bit open loop um
at times, but you don't you usually
never want to be have H be too large
otherwise you're executing too open
loop.
Um now we talked about how we can make
planning closed loop which is instead of
um
instead of executing the entire action
sequence you can just execute only the
first planned action. So, we're still
going to plan a a sequence of actions
because we need to consider uh not just
the first action, but how all of our
actions are going to affect future
rewards. But then we'll execute only the
first one, observe the resulting state,
and then we will then replan an an
action sequence starting at that new
next state.
Um, and then we can also like before,
um, kind of also add the data to our
data set, um, and periodically refit our
model based off of the latest data. Um,
this is something uh, this algorithm
right here is something called model
predictive control. It's very very
common in um, in certain robotic systems
uh, like like very widely used. It's
also used in um other kind of simple
control systems as well where you can
model uh kind of like lower dimensional
systems. Um it's quite it can be quite
effective for legged robots as well uh
where you have you're trying to learn
models and um you're able to plan uh
over kind of the next couple seconds uh
to figure out what um what will lead to
good uh what will lead to good
performance over the next couple
seconds.
Um, and this sort of replanning, uh,
when you actually
are considering a new plan at the next
time step, if something changes or if
you made a mistake, you slipped or
something, this replanning allows you to
actually consider a completely different
course of action. Um, and uh, yeah, and
and for example, correct for not just
for um changing environments, it can
also actually correct for model errors.
Uh and so generally this sort of
approach um if your model is accurate in
um a large part of the state space but
in some parts of the state space it's
inaccurate uh this sort of approach ends
up actually being a lot more robust to
those kinds of model errors. Yeah,
that's a good question. So if there are
multiple correct paths uh the question
is will and that sort kind of kind of
multimodality will that lead to like
oscillation between those different
paths. Um it certainly can lead to that
if you're replanning all the time and
you might kind of start start going in
one direction and then maybe say like oh
maybe I'll go in a different direction.
Um sometimes you also won't see that if
the state kind of indicates that you've
clearly committed to one direction. Um
but so sometimes you see it, sometimes
you don't. Uh the other way to
accommodate this and also actually
address computational challenges is that
you can warmstart your plan um for any
given time step to basically the plan
from the previous time step. Uh and so
if you had planned a t to a t plus h and
at the next time step you are planning
uh based off of s t +1 you're planning a
t +1 to t +1 + h. Then what you can do
is you can actually warm start this uh
using the um everything but the first
time step of this previous plan and then
you'll actually already have and then
randomly initialize the last action and
you'll already have um some kind of
initial plan that is sensible and so you
don't have to run as long of an
optimization procedure
and it also helps you commit to the um
to the previous action in the previous
Yeah, you can you instead of randomly
initializing uh for example um in our
sampling based thing you could uh yeah
either here or in a sampling based
approach you could initialize close to
the previous plan. You could also add
some noise or add some variance to your
sampling distribution uh so that you're
not like only considering that
particular plan.
Cool. Um so replanning helps with
nondeterministic environments. It also
is really really useful for model
errors. uh it is also compute intensive.
So it the warm starting can be helpful
um [clears throat] if you're actually
replanning at every single time step. It
means that every single time step you're
kind of reconsidering what action to
take and so it also can uh introduce uh
additional compute challenges as well.
Um sometimes you have something in the
middle where you'll have some planning
horizon. Uh but then maybe you'll plan
um not every one step but every like
three steps or every 10 steps or
something like that where maybe your
horizon is something like 110 steps.
Yeah. So it's an interesting question.
So the question was like as you're
learning and getting more data um
presumably your model is going to get
better and you have more confidence in
your model and so maybe um in so far as
this is really useful for correcting for
model errors you might be able to replan
less um less frequently when you have a
better model. Um so that that is
certainly um like yeah like very viable
and usually at some point you will have
some kind of final model that you're
using after the learning process and you
could kind of reoptimize you could use
different hyperparameters with regard to
like replanning for that final policy
versus during the learning process. Uh
and during the learning process it can
also be valuable like the model errors
also help you explore to some extent um
because you're going to be exploring
exactly the regions where the model is
inaccurate because because you'll be
incentivized to exploit any
inaccuracies.
>> Yeah. So the question is uh it seems
like this is an off- policy algorithm
and um and does it make sense like how
do you choose that policy? Uh so yes
this is an off policy algorithm. we
don't need to be using data from our
current policy. Uh you can actually use
a pretty broad policy and it makes sense
to use a pretty broad broad policy
because um then you'll get a model
that's accurate in more places uh
assuming that your model is expressive
and can fit that broader data
distribution.
Okay,
so far we've covered planning with
models. So we plan a sequence of
actions. We can do this either with
gradient descent or sampling. We then
update the model using data collected
through this uh planning process and we
can replan to help account for mistakes.
Um this is a pretty simple way to use a
learned model. Um, it's also one of the
things that's like I think really cool
about this is if you have a model that's
quite good, you can actually plug in
different rewards or different goals at
test time even uh and get a policy that
can follow like that can like for
example if you have a model that's good
um at like like universally good then
and you have a robot that's trying to
walk then with that same exact model you
can use this process at test time and
say I want you to run forwards I want
you to walk backwards I want you to
crouch. Uh and this kind of model is um
is quite task agnostic.
Um the downside is it's comput intensive
at test time and so you need to account
for this and if you have if it's you
have an expensive model and expens
expensive planning process um this kind
of planning at test time might not be
suitable.
Uh and the last thing is we we've been
talking about this for short horizon
problems. This is not applicable to long
horizon problems unless you have a
shaped reward function. Uh so if you
have a shaped reward function that is
telling you a lot about what a good
state is versus what a bad state is. For
example, u maybe you have an an infinite
horizon problem that that you want to
walk forward forever. You want to learn
a policy that can walk forward forever,
but you have a very dense reward
function that's like forward velocity.
Uh then you can plan for a short horizon
in a way that approximates the long
horizon problem.
But if you have a long horizon problem
that doesn't have a very dense reward
signal, then uh this is not a good
approach.
Cool. And part part of the reason for
this is um is the accuracy of the model.
Another part of this is that uh it's
very like it's going to be expensive to
be planning out a very long horizon
sequence of actions um because you're
not uh like you're not learning a policy
in this case.
Okay. Um,
now the question is can we train a
policy using this model? Um, and the the
first option here is you could actually
distill a planner's actions into a
policy. So you could store these actions
and then train a policy to match these
actions.
uh this would um this would address the
compute intensive problem and this would
make it a lot cheaper because then you
just need to run a forward pass through
the neural network to get your actions.
Um this doesn't address the the horizon
problem though because we're still going
to be using this procedure to optimize
for actions.
Um and then in terms of handling using
models for longer horizon problems uh
there's two main solutions.
Um
the first solution is that right now
we're optimizing for a sum of rewards
from t to t plus h.
And if we want to optimize for a longer
horizon of rewards. So far we are only
we the way that we would have to do that
is by optimizing over a longer horizon
of actions which gets higher and higher
dimensional.
But another thing that you could do is
that if you have a value function
or like an estimate of a value function,
then you could actually use that value
function to help this process where
instead of trying to maximize the sum of
rewards for the next h time steps, you
could optimize for the sum of rewards
for the next eight time steps plus your
estimate of the value of the state that
you end up at uh after taking those h
actions.
Uh and so
the this would end up with an algorithm
where you're learning both a model and a
value function. And then you would be
running this planning process. You'd be
considering a bunch of different actions
over some horizon. And then past that
horizon, you're just asking your value
function, is that a good state or a bad
state? Uh and so this is um
a valid way to combine planning with
value based RL uh in order to select uh
select actions.
Yeah. So the question is um why why use
the model? Why not just uh like use a Q
function for example? Um the
this is why I didn't want to spend too
much time on this method is that in this
case you are learning a value function.
and you have to learn a value function
and a model like you're learning a lot
of different things and there's a lot of
moving pieces. Um there is still some
merit to using this and it for example
if you know the model um then you're
going to get a better estimate of future
rewards than your value function. And so
you can actually get a lower um you can
actually use this to kind of plan out
future actions. Like in games, it's
actually really common to kind of do
kind of these rollouts through your
model of the game. Um, and then uh to to
the extent that it's computationally
feasible and then use your value
function uh just because it's going to
reduce uh it's going to be more
accurate. It's give you a better
estimate of how good your action is. Um
but it's only if you have a really good
model or if it's practical and not too
difficult to learn a good model.
And then the other approach which I'm
thinking
we don't have too much time and so I I
think I might cover this second approach
um
on Friday
uh and then um and then kind of go
through the um go through the case
study.
So um
let's talk a bit about the
um let's talk about this case study. So
this case study is is actually going to
be an example of using planning um for
dextrous manipulation.
And the reason why I want to cover this
case study briefly is that um in my mind
is actually still one of the most
impressive robotics results with a
five-fingered hand. uh and it's also has
some pretty nice comparisons that are
elucidating about what is important for
good performance in modelbased RL and
planning.
Um so the way it works is the states are
the position of the hand and the
position of objects.
This assumes that you know the kind of
the the 3D position of an object which
you can estimate with a computer vision
system um or put like motion capture
markers on the objects.
Uh whereas the hand position you can use
like sensors in the hand itself in order
to measure the hand positions. Uh the
action space is to control a five
fingered hand. It has 24 different
joints that you can control. uh and the
reward is to target some kind of object
trajectory where there's also some
penalty for dropping the object.
Uh the model is going to be actually
pretty simple. Um there the model is
going to be a neural network with two
hidden layers of size 500. Uh but it's
also going to train an ensemble of
neural networks. And this is something
that I kind of an example that I wanted
to look at because this this kind of
ensembling approach can also help with
model errors. Uh and the way this works
is instead of just training one neural
network, you'll train three neural
networks with different random
initializations and different kind of
mini batch sampling
just with different random seeds. And
then if one model is like very
optimistic about what will happen, that
can be counterbalanced by like errors in
other models. And it essentially gives
you a way to uh to kind of
um deal with the fact that models will
have uh different like errors in
different ways.
So you're not going to exploit the
errors in any one model.
Uh and then the planner it's a modified
version of the cross entropy method. So
it's going to be using iterative uh
resampling of the actions and um
it's going to the the modifications are
that it's going to use this kind of
softer um reward weighted mean and it
does some sort of temporal smoothing on
the actions to encourage and search over
actions that um that are taking smoother
trajectories.
Um but you can basically think of it as
like cross entropy method or this kind
of iterative sampling based
optimization. Uh and then they alternate
between uh in step one collecting 30
trajectories um and updating uh the
model.
Okay. Um so then in the simulate
experiments we are going to see a
comparison to some model free methods
methods that are not using a dynamics
model. uh we'll see soft actor and an
algorithm called natural policy gradient
which is a policy gradient method and
then we'll also see some modelbased
methods uh so the proposed method is
called pdddm um we'll also see uh an
algorithm called mpo uh a different kind
of uh planner called pets um and then
also a method that doesn't use ensembles
and doesn't use iterative resampling
uh and here are some videos of what
you're able to do with this method So um
we're running planning at um in the loop
of uh actually execution and we see that
it's able to learn how to rotate uh the
bouting balls in the hand and also write
uh digits on this piece of paper. And we
see that if we plot the kind of reward
where higher is better over the number
of data points that are collected in
order to fit the model or or in the the
policy in the case of model free
methods. Uh we see that first for this
really complex task uh only the proposed
method is able to solve it uh because
it's really challenging. Um and we also
see that some of the methods that for
example don't do iterative resampling uh
that for example just do random sampling
shown in yellow uh get very po poor
performance because you're not able to
get to a good part of the distribution
and hone in on good actions.
uh and in the case of handwriting which
is a little bit easier uh we see that
some methods are able to get good
performance like SACE and natural policy
gradient get high performance but they
need far far more data than this
modelbased method which is shown in
green and so the modelbased method is
using like maybe on the order of 100,000
time steps of data whereas um the model
free methods are using like half a
million time steps
um so it's a lot more efficient than
model free methods. It's also more
performant than other model based
methods. Um we also see that the model
needs to be sufficiently large. You also
need this ensemble for good performance.
Um and there's different trade-offs with
regard to the planning horizon. So you
don't want to plan for too long into the
future because that's too high
dimensional.
Uh and then they also did it on a real
hand uh using the method that we talked
about. Uh data efficiency is really
important for fragile hardware. This
robot hand is very fragile. We there
actually is one at Stanford in the Gates
building and I think all the students
are like afraid to touch it because they
don't want to break it. Uh and then they
have to figure out how to fix it because
it's also really complicated. Uh and the
success rate uh for 90° turns is
actually around 100% after just four
hours of data. Um for 180°ree turns,
which is a bit harder, uh it's the
success rate is a bit lower, but you're
still able to make significant
performance with four hours of data. Um
they also had the they reset the system
when it dropped a ball using another
robot. Um look like this setup.
Cool. Um that's it for today. Uh next
time we'll cover the last part about
modelbased RL and uh RL with multiple
tasks and goals.